Guide to the Herbert C. (Herbert Coffin) Jones Papers, 1903-1954
Department of Special Collections
Herbert C. (Herbert Coffin) Jones Papers,
1903-1954
Special Collections M0099
Jones, Herbert C. (Herbert Coffin), b1881?
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Herbert C. Jones, 1954.
Biographical Note
Herbert C. Jones was born in Oskaloosa, Iowa, where his father taught in Penn College. He received his grammar school and high school education in San Jose, California, and his university training at Stanford University, where he completed his bachelor's degree in 1902. In 1904 he graduated from the Stanford school of Law. After graduation, Mr. Jones spent a short period in the County Clerk's Office, Santa Clara County, then began to practice law in San Jose where he since has maintained law offices. Mr. Jones took a leading part in the civic and community affairs of San Jose and Santa Clara County and manifested an interest, as well, in state and national political events. On January 2, 1913 he was elected to the California State Senate, in the first recall election of a state legislative official in California. Senator Jones served as State Senator for twenty-two years, 1913 through 1934. The Jones Papers include material from 1912 to 1954, however, because Mr. Jones continued to follow closely state political activity after his term of official service.
Mr. Jones gave his papers to the Stanford Libraries' California Collection in 1955, for the interest and use of students of California history and politics in the twentieth century.
The papers were catalogued during the summers, 1956-and 1957, by a graduate student (Donna Keyes) in the Stanford Department of History.
R
I. Quantity, Scope, and Nature of the Collection.
The Collection consists of:
CORRESPONDENCE. Letters to and from Senator Jones. Correspondence with individuals, groups, organizations, companies, fellow legislators, etc., pertaining principally to past, current, or future legislation in the years 1912 through 1954. Also there are letters such as those from applicants for appointive positions in State committees or apencies, and letters of congratulation to Senator Jones upon his re-election to Legislature, or letters of appreciation for his work in defeating or promoting a given legislative measure. All Correspondence is filed in chronological order.
REFERENCE MATERIAL. Legislation, copies of Senate and assembly Bills and Constitutional Amendments, material relating to Bills, explaining or justifying them; Newspaper clippings and magazine articles pertaining to specific legislative measures; proceedings, hearings, reports, etc. of Senate and/or Assembly permmanent or temporary committees. Reference Material is filed chronologically and within this division, alphabetically according to topic,
HANDBOOKS for Legislature. Sessions: 1903, 1911, 1913, 1915, 1917, 1919, 1921, 1923, 1925, 1927, 1929, 1933, 1935, 1937, 1939, 1941. The Handbooks for each legislative session are useful guides in discovering on which Senate Committees Mr. Jones served as Chairman or was member.
BOOKS. All books in the Jones Collection are listed in the Bibliography Card File.
PAMPHLETS, PERIODICALS, GOVERNMENT PUBLICATIONS, and other material of this nature are arranged chronologically from 1903 through 1953 in the Pamphlet Boxes, nos. 1 through 45. Pamphlet Box no. 46 is a collection of Directories of State and County Officials of California, from 1925 through 1937.
BIBLIOGRAPHY CARD FILE. A list of all Books, Pamphlets, Periodicals, Government Publications (State and Federal), etc. in the Collection that are not filed in folders along with the Correspondence and Reference Materials. The cards are arranged 1) Chronologically 1903 through 1953; and 2) Alphabetically by title or author of each publication, within the years.
NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS. Individual Newspaper Clippings which have been preserved because they pertain to a given legislative matters, are filed in the Correspondence or the Reference Material files, in some cases alphabetically according to topic of the clipping and in other cases attached to letters as enclosures. Newspaper Clippings which report on an entire Legislative Session during a given year are arranged in the eight Leather-Bound Scrapbooks in the Collection. (see page 3 of this Guide) Newspaper Clippings which could not be identified by topic, date or source are placed in the four Brown Paper Folios in the Collection (see page 3 of this Guide).
PHOTOGRAPH of John Randolph Heynes, friend of Mr. Franklin Hichborn and of Mr. Jones.
List of Newspaper clippings in leather-backed scrapbook
Bills, (copies of) Introduced by Senator H.C. Jones, Legislative Session, 1921.
Newspaper Clippings on topics and action of Legislature, 1923, book no. 1
Newspaper Clippings on topics and action of Legislature, 1923, book no. 2
Newspaper Clippings on Legislature, 1925
Jones, H.C. Political Campaign for Senatorship, 1926. 28th Senatorial District. Newspaper Clippings, several letters.
Newspaper Clippings on topics and action of Legislature, 1931. Clippings from San Francisco Chronicle, S.F. Examiner, and The Sacramento Bee.
Newspaper Clippings on Legislature, 1933.
Senate Investigating Committee. Newspaper Clippings of progress of the Investigation of the Rolph Administration, 1933.
List of Newspaper Clippings in Brown Paper Folios
Newspaper Clippings, pamphlets, etc. For 1914, 1915, 1916. 1917, 1918.
Newspaper Clippings on Legislation, 1921 Session. King Tax Bill, etc.
Newspaper Clippings from The Sacramento Bee, 1929 and Miscellaneous Clippings, 1931.
Newspaper Article and Clippings, Miscellaneous, Business notes of Senator Jones.
I I. The Nature of the Collection:
Mr. Jones himself speaks for the nature of the collection in excerpts From two letters.
Excerpt from a letter from Mr. Jones, San Jose, January 4, 1956, to Mr. J. Terry Bender, Chief, Division of Special Collections, Stanford Libraries, Stanford University:
The period covered by my own collection deals with numerous phases of the political and economic life of California over a quarter of a century.
The complete circle traveled by the Prohibition or liquor control movement, beginning with the regulation of such matters as the hours of liquor sale, proximit to universities and schools, then on to the local option movements in cities, supervisorial districts and counties, and then to state regulation and on to national prohibition, then the repeal of national prohibition and back to the starting point.
The slow and steady increase in the political influence of organized labor.
The development of flood control, including the levees along the Sacramento, the bitter struggle between the Sutter Basin, leveeing the waters from its area, only to force higher levels on orchards and farm areas around Marysville, the dynamiting of such levees, and, in turn, the patrolling of them by men armed with rifles.
The growth of the pension movement for teachers, municipal employees, old-age pensions.
The insistence on increasing governmental regulation--inspection of foods, protection of drinking water, sanitation along our rivers and shore fronts, safety codes in building, fruit standardization, minimum prices, fair trade laws, etc.
The converting of the old Railroad Commission into the Public Utilities Commission
The regulating of banks, building and loan associations, insurance companies--how much for the protection of the public, and how much to stifle competition?
The increase of State expenditure and State taxes--18,000,000 dollars for State expenses in Hiram Johnson's first administration and 1,081,000,000 under Governor Warren--why the increase out-runs population. The foregoing are but examples of the trends covered during my own period of service in the Legislature.
Excerpt from letter from Mr. Jones to Dr. Edgar E. Robinson at Stanford University, dated: San Jose, California, March 23, 1956.
The hope I had in mind in placing the material at Stanford was that it might be of assistance to students of California politics. I served under six governors, beginning with Hiram Johnson and extending down to Erank Merriam. This has been described as an explosive period in California politics. Certainly the Johnson campaign of 1910 and his administration ushered in a new era in California. The impact of his administration has been felt during the succeeding half century. His was the era when Theodore Roosevelt was President and we had a political up-surge that produced state governors like Charles Evans Hughes of New York, Robert LaFollette in Wisconsin, Woodrow Wilson in New Jersey, and Joe Folk in Missouri.
Their reforms, attempted or accomplished, were numerous, and the shift in public opinion and the development of the social viewpoint as against the old Laissez-faire doctrine were fundamental and far reaching.
There followed many problems with which the modern day students of history and government must be greatly interested. A few of these developments come readily to mind.
First, there was the implementing of public expression through the new instruments of democracy:
The Initiative
The Referendum
The Recall
Women's Suffrage
Direct election of U.S. Senators
Regulation of expenditures in political campaigns and publicizing the same.
These instruments for the expression of public opinion were used in dealing with Prohibition, the Red Light Abatement Act, and Race Track Gambling.
There was then afforded a chance to see how they have worked out, some of the abuses and to what extent results have been disappointing. These are subjects of interest to students.
Then in the field of taxation, there are such problems us:
The mounting public debt
Whether republics are able successfully to cope with these burdens.
For example, in California, Hiram Johnson ran the entire state government during the first year of his administration for approximately 18,000,000 dollars. Governor Knight's budget today (1956) is 1,770,000, 000 dollars. If these figures are put on a chart, they are startling and show the mounting of State expenditure far exceeds the rate of population increase.
There is the study of new and expanded State activities. During Hiram Johnson's time came the first State highway. At the session in which the first gasoline tax bill was introduced for one cent a gallon sach was the public outcry that no attempt was made even to bring the bill out of Committee. The next session came around and public opinion had so changed that a bill for two cents a gallon went sailing through the Legislature with scarcely a ripple of opposition.
The whole program for State highways is a most interesting study--how little we realizer when the first bond issues for 18,000,000 and 15,000,000 dollars were approved, what the highway system was ultimately to become.
Then there has been the development of the pensions--teacher's pensions, pensions for firemen, policemen, municipal and county employees, etc. The old-age pension, required many sessions of study and investigation before the Legislature dared to act. In later years there has been a scramble among Legislators to lead the fight for even higher old age allowances.
In the field of regulation of utilities, the cry of the railroads was that the State keep its hands off. Their slogan was that country is best governed which is governed least, that the power to tax is the power to destroy. Then came the jitneys and motor vehicles carrying passengers and freight, and over-night there was a reversal in the traditional attitude of the railroads; they wanted their opponents taxed and regulated out of existence; it made a difference whose ox was gored.
There is a vast field of public health legislation--the inspection of public food markets, restaurants, barber shops, slaughter houses; also State supervision of fresh water streams, and subsidies to County tuberculosis hospitals.
Then followed the whole program for the supervision of adoptions, orphans' homes, rest homes.
The licensing of doctors, lawyers, banks, building and loan associations, accountants, realtors and insurance companies, extended to contractors, beauty parlors--a vast field of regulation in which there is a question of whether the protection of the public is not mixed with a desire to restrict competition.
Then there is the development of the fee system--the charging of tuition at Stanford (1 put through the bill for the Trustees legalizing this); charges for out-of-state students at the University of California; the entering wedge for tuition charges and the State University and State colleges; the attempt during the depression to impose a tuition system in high schools and to take the Budgetary control from school boards and place it with Boards of Supervisors.
One of the biggest subjects of all is water.
In the 1915 session I was made chairman of the Senate Committee on Drainage, Swamp and Overflowed Lands. This was because a Chairman was wanted who came from a part of the State not affected by the bitter controversy over the Sutter Basin development. The reclaiming of this ruly vast area area by levees was backing flood waters on the farms and orchards around Marysville. The dykes were dynamited by those whose lands were thus flooded. The Sutter Basin owners in turn patrolled the levees with armed guards. There was almost a state of civil war.
The theory then was to get rid of surplus waters. They were looked upon as the common enemy. A long notch was cut in the east bank of the Sacramento River, known as the Tisdale Wier, through which the flood waters of the river flowed over into the Sutter Basin and moved slowly down to join the waters of the American River. Here another wier was cut, this time in the west bank of the Sacramento River, and the water allowed to flow as a vast inland sea down the Yolo Basin and on toward Suisun Bay. The theory was to rush the waters down to the Bay by fast express' rather than slow freight.
Six years went by. Then came Colonel Marshall before the legislature in 1921 backed by the land owners of the Tulare region whose orchards were dying from lack of water. There followed the fascinating story of his plan for transporting the surplus waters of the Sacramento Valley to the deficient areas of the San Joaquin Valley in a giant east-side canal. The Legislature appropriated approximately 1,000,000 dollars over the next ten years to have the plan studied by the State Engineer. He made his Report in 1931. In 1933 we passed the Central Valley Act.
It was I who, at the request of the State Grange and the League of Municipalities, put in the amendment in the Central Valley Act which provided for the construction by the State of the transmission line from Shasta to Antioch. This put the fight into the Central Act which caused the power companies to invoke the referendum. The measure, however, was sustained by the voters at the Special Election on December 19, 1933. In the midst of the depression of the `30's the State could not float bonds for 170,000,000 to build the project and so appealed to the Federal Government to take over. This it was placed in the hands of the U.S. Reclamation Bureau. The Bureau instead of transporting the water either through Marshall's proposed east-side canal, or the channel of the San Joaquin River by a series of booster dams, as recommended by the State Engineer, constructed its giant Delta-Mendota Canal running 120 miles along the west side of the San Joaquin Valley from Tracy to Mendota.
The tremendous increase in the State's population today is centering a new attention to water. Involved are all the problems of State vs. Federal financing and operation, the controversy over the 160 acre limitation, and the effort by are s of dearth to modify the count of origin law.
All this challenges the attention of the student of California history.
Running through all these instances just cited, is the shifting in the public viewpoint from the old laissez-faire doctrine toward the theory of the Welfare State with ever increasing public expenditure and public debt--municipal, state, and federal.
All these are problems which are pressing on our communities and states with increasing insistance. They naturally are questions in which the student of history and government in our universities must be profoundly interested if he would fit himself to plot the course of Society in the future.
An important feature whould be the interpretation that those of us who are identified with Hiram Johnson and succeeding governors, such as Stephens and Young, could give in clarifying the material.
There are many things that do not become clear unless accompanied by such personal interpretation. One example is why the candidacy of Stephen M. White for U.S. Senator and Judge McGuire for Governor ran hand in hand and were mutually supported until the very end of the campaign. Stephen M. White's support was withdrawn from McGuire. Franklin Hichborn furnishes the explanation for this.
In the case of C.C. Young, there was the incident when he was hesitating to announce his candidacy for Governor, when Franklin Hichborn summoned Senator Inman down from Sacramento and myself up from San Jose. We went into a huddle with Young who still wanted a few days to make up his mind. The others of us told Young that he would have to announce that night or it would be too late; that the next day Mayor Cryer of los Angeles expected to make his announcement. We finally shoved Young over the brink and made him issue his announcement.
The next morning Senator Inman and I called on Hiram Johnson. He scowled at us as we entered his office. His first words were, You have nominated Young, now elect him. Johnson's choice would have been Neumiller of Stockton.
The difficulty in interpreting the collections of contemporary history is that unfortunately the men of that era are fast dropping from the scene. Mr. Hichborn is 87 years of age with health not too good. Senator Inman has passed away. My colleague and seatmate, Senator W.J. Carr of Pasadena, whom I visited last December, I found in bed and kept alive by an oxygen tank. Senator Frank Benson of Santa Clara County, one of the leaders in the Hiram Johnson administration, suffers from a stroke of paralysis that makes it difficult for him to get around.
This invaluable aid in interpreting the documents and events of the Johnson era will shortly be gone.
Guide the Correspondence and Reference Materials
File Drawers no. 1 through 17: 1912 - 1954
Organization of the Correspondence and Reference Material
All Correspondence and Reference Material is arranged Chronologically From 1912 through 1954.
All Correspondence and Reference Material is arranged Alphabetically within the Chronological divisions.
From the beginning year of Senator Herbert C. Jones' term in the California legislature (1913) to 1925, Correspondence is filed alphabetically by name of the correspondence. For this period, 1913-1925, the Correspondence is filed according to name of the sender or recepient of the letters, regardless of the topic or subject matter of the letters. Pamphlets, Newspaper clippings, etc. that pertain to a given legislative topic are filed in folders identified as Reference Material. Example: 1917, Reference File. These Reference Material folders are place in the file drawers after the Correspondence folders for each of the years of Legislature from 1913 to 1925.
Beginning with 1925, the material in the collection was more clearly arranged (upon receipt of the collection) according to subject matter. Therefore, most of the material from 1925 on could be filed alphabetically according to subject matter or topic, rather than by the name of the correspondent. Of course, not all of the material could be filed by subject matter. So it has been done in this manner: Whenever there was no evident subject or topic of a given letter, the letter was filed under the name of the correspondent. From 1925 on, there are for each legislative year three groups of folders:
A group of folders of Correspondence filed according to the name of the person or group to whom Senator Jones wrote or from whom he received letters.
A group of folders of Correspondence and Reference Materials, integrated, filed according to Subject Matter of the correspondence.
A group of folders of Correspondence in which there are letters filed according to subject matter if such is evident, or by name of correspondent.
Because the material in the collection after 1925 was more clearly arranged according to legislative or other topics of concern to Senator Jones, the bulk of the material from 1925 on has been filed topically, that is, by subject matter. This made unnecessary the earlier method of filing (1913-1925) some material (pamphlets, clippings, etc., relating to given legislative topics) in folders separate from Correspondence, known as Reference Files. Subsequent to 1925, these two groupings have been incorporated into one grouping of folders known as Legislative Correspondence, filed by Subject Matter. That is, Correspondence and reference material on Adoption or Initiative and Referendum, have been filed together. It was necessary, however, to continue filing; some letters by name of Correspondent rather than by subject matter. In many cases the letters do not pertain to a given legislative measure or topic and thus for each legislative year there is a group of folders of correspondnece arranged alphabetically according to the name of the correspondent. These are the letters referred to in 1) above, and are identified as: legislative Correspondence, files according name of correspondent.
After-Session Correspondence. Correspondence (with some reference material) after the biennial legislative session closes (may-june). This division is the material referred to in section 3) above. The After-Session Correspondence usually dates from the close of a given legislative session to the opening of another. For example, this group of folders will contain correspondence From June 1920 through 1928, to the opening (January) session of legislature in 1981. However, correspondence dated 1928, which pertains specifically to a topic of legislation to be dealt with in the 1929, the coming session, will be filed with the correspondence of the 1929 session. That is, letters of the late months of 1928 that pertain to coming legislative business will be filed with the 1929 legislative folders, in the Legislative Correspondence filed by Subject Matter, 1929, if the topic of the letter can be ascertained; -- if the letter is about a general matter which does not become a principal topic of legislation in the 1929 session, it will remain grouped with the other 1928 letters in the 1927-1928 After-Session Correspondence file.
In the 1918-1925 Folders, before the creation of a grouping known as After-Session Correspondence, the correspondence from non-legislature years is arranged thus:
Since the California Legislature met biennially, the bulk of Senator Jones' correspondence falls under odd-numbered years. 1913, 1915, 1917, etc.; usually the correspondence in even-numbered years, 1916, 1918, 1920, etc., has been incorporated with Folders of correspondence dated in the odd-numbered, legislative session years.
Example: Part of the correspondence dated 1916 is filed with the 1915 and part of it with the 1917 folders, depending upon the month in which a certain letter was written. Most even-numbered year correspondence in the collection pertains to legislative business of the previous or coming legislative session. Therefore, the first six months of correspondence dated 1916 will be found filed with the 1915 legislative correspondence folder. The correspondence dated in the last six months of 1916 is filed with the 1917 correspondnece folders.